of an IT
professional what are
they well some people have different
opinions on this and before I finish
this video or even start this video this
is something of a tongue-and-cheek joke
I have to make sure to put that there
because when I tell you what the virtues
are you're going to be like that's not a
virtue that's a vice why would you
encourage people to do that and I have
to say that because I mentioned one of
them and got kind of cancelled
by a group of people who thought that in
fact it caused them to make videos about
why they should not follow me as a
mentor I'm not even kidding so no drama
what are the virtues the first virtue
and by the way let's just go out into
the internet my friends I mean when has
a when has a live stream search of the
internet ever been a bad thing what are
the
virtues of uh of IT professional God
look at all my
stuff okay oh look at that oh that's so
happy Integrity honesty courage and good
judgment yeah
no those definitely are the virtues but
I I want you to to understand some of
the other
virtues uh I didn't even I spell it I
did I spell it right virtues
[Music]
virtues um I'm going to seed this a
little bit I'm going to
yeah
yeah yeah the virtue of hubus um this be
great Virtues Of programmers okay um
this is what I was actually looking for
and you will probably hear about this on
the internets um The Virtue C don't be a
dick yeah that is kind of one of them
um this again this video is more about
the the personality type that goes along
with being this and I am going to talk a
little bit in this video about I'm going
to tell a couple stories of when it has
happened and when it hasn't happened my
personal um uh experience with this um
but there's a lot of commentary about it
programs that do have these
virtues um and I mean if you go all the
way back
back this is the original post and it
was made by Larry wall from programming
Pearl long time ago uh if you don't know
who Larry wall is Larry wall is one of
the most amazing um uh technologist who
have ever lived uh creative Pearl and
and if you know if you didn't live
through the 90s you don't know how big a
deal Larry wall was R Schwarz I actually
used to hang with him a little bit in
Oregon uh wrote learning Pearl um
and yeah actually went to a karaoke bar
with him once and so Larry wall is the
originator of the three I'm going to
zoom in on this because this is a very
very old web page uh and we're going to
read about these these qualities and
we're going to read um Larry Wall's uh
you know definition of these and before
before you say why do I care what the
creator of pearl thinks about
everything this guy created the most
significant programming language
probably of the
entire I would say probably all the
entire 9s decade if not '90s probably
and into and to this day I mean I I work
for a very huge multinational and
there's over 80,000 Lions of brco doing
all kinds of stuff I wrote several
thousands of lines of code that's that's
managing to this day probably about
52,000 machines uh for audit compliance
in parole um lot of the the hackers out
there wrote in Paro so don't don't
discount what Larry wall has to say just
because he was the creator of Pearl and
you think Pearl is a language you
shouldn't care about because somebody on
the internet told you Pearl sucked
there's a video about that by the way go
go read that uh or watch that or
whatever so let's actually hear what he
had to say about the the the virtues of
a good programmer and of course if you
know Larry you know that most of this is
tongue and cheek from the very beginning
the first one is laziness the quality
that makes you go to great effort to
reduce overall energy expenditure it
makes you write labor saving programs
that other people will find useful and
document what you wrote so that you
don't have to answer so many questions
about it hence the first great virtue of
a programmer and I would say you know a
technologist is
laziness let's talk about let's talk
about lazy for for a
second I love being lazy being lazy
means that I make things that I don't so
I don't have to do them over again right
and let me give you an example how many
times have I redone the Boost every year
right I'm redoing the same stuff because
most of the content changed but some of
the content hasn't changed and why am I
redoing it I'm too lazy for that so I'm
going to make a whole bunch of little
videos and then I just have to replace
the video that got changed from last
year that's the lazy way to do it right
the lazy way is to only fix the things
that need to be fixed and you don't want
to be changing stuff all the time right
so there are many many times where the
laziness laziness laziest way is also
the most efficient it's easier and so
that's why that is a virtue does that
mean that you do the least amount of
work
possible
maybe you just can't pull a Scotty by
the way don't pull a Scotty don't pull a
Scotty what do I mean by that that
should be a thing this goes in laziness
Scotty was never lazy Scotty just always
wanted more credit so oh can't be done
captain no no no we're all going to die
there's no way I can do that in time and
then he would do it
anyway my favorite line by the way my
favorite my favorite line from any Star
Trek actually there's two but this is
probably the second most favorite I'll
tell you the first and another video so
my probably my one of my favorite lines
ever written by a newer generation Star
Trek writer was in Voyager when balana
Torres who's this really really badass
half clling on half human uh engineer
she's my favorite character in the
entire Star Trek series she's absolutely
amazing and she gets
asked um she gets asked by another
engineer uh well oh she no somebody
asked her how long it's this is related
to laziness someone asked her well how
long do you think it's going to take she
goes well let's see it's going to and
she does a little thing in her head she
goes I would say probably 3 to 5 days 3
to 5 days given given the amount of work
that we have to do and she and then the
other person is like an engineer or
something and he says wait a second
aren't you going to like pad your
estimate so that you look better when
you pull it out you know in under that
time and she looks straight at him and
she says no that would be
irresponsible it's basically the
voyagers riters like totally taking a
shot at the original Star Trek writers
of Scotty because balana Torres pulling
a Scotty is completely against her ethos
the the idea that you would lie about
your
estimate just to make yourself look
better you know and ab so that they oh
he said you couldn't do oh my God you
did it anyway yeah I tried I got I dug
down deep and I did it and the whole
time he knew that you could do it in a
shorter amount of time that would be
dishonest so don't do that that's kind
of related to the laziness thing uh yeah
dishonesty is not one of these
virtues uh D yeah that's the PM the
project manager yeah let them lie about
it impatience the anger you feel when
the computer is being
lazy this makes you uh write programs
that don't just react to your needs but
actually anticipate your needs or at
least pretend to hence the second grade
virtual programmer is
impatience yeah we don't like waiting
around for things do we we really don't
programmers don't like laying around
Engineers don't like waiting around like
no I'm just going to make that thing in
fact one of the best thing I say this
all the time one of the best reasons to
learn a code is you don't have to wait
to talk to somebody who knows how to do
it I have a story about that so there's
this guy my my my ex- brother-in-law who
had ideas about everything he was always
coming at me with the latest idea of
what would be a cool site or what would
be a great idea for a
startup but he was always trying to get
me to make it like why aren't you making
this one time I told him I said why
don't you learn the code and make it
yourself shut him right
up totally shut him
up totally totally shut him up cuz he
was like oh
yeah but if if you're impatient if
you're impatient then you can make it
yourself yeah even if even if you don't
want to become I look I've told people
all day today and many other days I
actually don't like to code I like what
I get from the coding money and apps I
want programs I
want so I'm
impatient and I'm lazy and I want to
make things that make me you know save
my time so I can go get on my bike or
that keep me uh you know I know
impatient I want to learn the code
because I want to make a thing another
thing about impatience is let's say you
want to re you end up making reusable
code because if you do the code right
even though it takes a bit longer the
next time you want to do the same thing
oh I don't know like parse yaml
properly then you can go back and do it
because you impatient you just go reuse
the thing you already made right so
impatience is another
virtue um and and then the last one is
is hubris and this is the one that
nearly got me cancelled actually there's
a video out there you can go read it you
can go see it watch it you can't read a
video
Rob um go watch it and you can go see
what they say uh but I suggested and
this is this is what I was referring to
this is not me saying this this is Larry
wall saying I am not saying you should
have hubis Larry wall is saying it
cancel every wall oh wait everybody
already did um he's also I hope he's
still alive he's been struggling with
health problems please you know don't be
a dick um excessive Pride the sort of
thing Zeus zaps you
for uh also the quality that makes you
write and maintain programs that other
people won't want to say bad things
about hence the third great virtue of a
programmer is
humorous
so I mean I don't think it's any news
flash to tell you that if you look up
the Webster whatever dictionary
definition of these words hubris is not
a good word it has nothing but
pejorative
meaning uh and that's not you know by
the way if you changed the P to a b it
would be beor and it's another Star Trek
reference Bora yeah be yeah anyway
excessive
Pride excessive Pride be proud of what
you make be German about
it so have people who have hubris
are less likely even though they have
impatience and
laziness they are less likely to put
[__]
out right they're more likely to take
time not unnecessarily unnecessary time
but to put something that is actually
good right to not just hack something
but to make something that has high
quality so so huis is a fun way to say
you actually care about the quality of
the thing you're making and I have a
story about that
I have a story about that
yeah
so I this is kind of a sad story I was
reporting quality issues and bugs in
software for almost a month and I was on
a call right before our delivery date
yep don't just ship it this is what this
this is
about I was on a call right before we
shipped uh a very big project a big
project and it was a conference call and
I was with my manager I'm not going to
tell you much more about the manager
except for I absolutely hated him one of
the worst managers I've ever had had no
ability to relate to us had no technical
acument at all and I was stuck working
for this guy because I got bought out my
inti inside of the company anyway um and
I said I said this code doesn't work he
said oh no he he got to the end of the
meeting but ready to launch and and they
said okay this is the last time we're
going to open the floor up does anybody
have anything to bring up before we
launch and I said well you know it
doesn't work like I like I mentioned in
that email and I like what are you
talking about I said well you know I I I
sent the email and I talked to you and
he like why do you have to boil the
water right now you always boiling the
water at the end I'm like well you asked
us to tell you and I you know I'm
obviously paraphrasing but he let me
have it this was a call with about 18
people on it and most of the people I
cared about that I worked with dayto day
knew it was a problem I had been telling
them about it as a problem and and I you
know and we thought what are we going to
do and they're like well they're going
to looks like they're going to ship it
anyway and I said okay it's not we can't
we can't ship it and said but I said
I've done everything I can I've
escalated it in every possible way and
so I could not get through that meeting
with good conscience without saying it
doesn't
work and uh Mr Robot they actually have
a story a similar story where uh it's
fictional but but Elliot they kept it
was the pentester and he kept finding
crap wrong and they got annoyed because
they wanted to go to their party so they
locked him in the like refrigerator or
something because he kept finding
problems he kept he was in you know he
kept like stop finding problems so I
found this
problem and they saidwell you did I said
I already did tell you and and they said
don't boil the water and ever since then
my my my wife she knows this story
inside and out and you know she calls me
all the time as a joke she goes yeah
it's cuz you're a water
boiler a water boiler is not somebody
who you know brings out critical flaws
and software before they get released
into production a water boiler is
somebody who just wants to hear them
self complain and I am sometimes that
guy so I will own that I will own that
and is it because of my excessive Pride
you know hubris I don't know maybe it's
because I'm obsessed with not releasing
stuff that's going to destroy the world
and believe me the software that I have
seen I was talking to dentist last miles
the other day about this because he's
working on the floating Point error uh
that is core to all kinds of stuff and
we joke about planes falling out of the
sky and trains colliding because that's
the level of bug that he's working on
and if it weren't for Dennis's
hubris it quite possibly people could
die you know if it weren't for if the
people who who put the spaghetti code
that is according to a NASA engineer who
o in under
oath uh testified that the problem for
the Toyota Camry accelerator's locking
was because there was too much code
people had just gone in there and made
incremental changes he called it Cru and
he called it spaghetti code so the
official cause of death for many people
who were suing in the in the Toyota
Camry versus whatever class action
lawsuit was spaghetti code and that
spaghetti code came about because people
were doing the minimum necessary to get
that assembly code firmware to work and
they had disabled the safeties that were
built into the software in the first
place I've talked about this story a
million times but I tell you what an
engineer who has hubis would never ever
have allowed that code to make it to
that level an engineer punching the
clock and doing a day-to-day
grind spaghetti go kills hubris saves
lives my friend hubris saves lives uh
I'm not gonna if you want to know about
the lawsuit I'll talk about it more
offline but if you don't it's a Toyota
Camry lawsuit where the accelerator
pedals stuck that's the
lawsuit and we actually found this once
as a group and we we found the actual
code we want to make merch that has the
code on the back and on the front it
says Spaghetti code
kills I think that would be some fun
merch I would love to write talk about
deadly software software that makes your
accelerator pedal stick
yeah not a good thing if you're in the
automotive industry so anyway hubris
that's what this is about um hubris is a
good thing hubris means that you care
about
something um and stuff and uh that's the
end of this video